<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-05-07T00:33:22-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">MIT Electric Vehicle Team (EVT)</title><entry><title type="html">Roaming on Battery Power!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023-4-27-roaming/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Roaming on Battery Power!" /><published>2023-04-27T06:25:30-04:00</published><updated>2023-04-27T06:25:30-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/roaming</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023-4-27-roaming/"><![CDATA[<p>Today we’re super excited to announce that our team just hit the first major milestone on the road to developing a hydrogen powered motorcycle! Our bike drives under its own power. In this case, the bike was powered by a Lithium battery. Here’s a few fun videos of it driving!</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/oQHbWxG8HFY" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/XX5TXS8L-wE" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="https://youtube.com/shorts/5WhaHTfYNqE?feature=share">Here’s another short driving clip,</a></p>

<h2 id="drivetrain-notes">Drivetrain Notes</h2>

<p>This was not completely without issues, we noticed while driving the bike that one of the belts connecting the second motor to the main drive shaft was slipping. This is a simple issue to fix but one that prevented us from trying to drive the bike any faster. Over the next few weeks, we’ll be doing the following.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Dropping out the V1 drivetrain and attempting to correct the belt slipping issue.</li>
  <li>Focusing on the design of the V2 drivetrain to get that mounted on the bike by mid-summer.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gen/blog/testing1.jpeg" width="45%" /> <img src="/assets/images/gen/blog/testing2.jpeg" width="45%" /></p>

<p>The V2 drivetrain will have a better mechanical design and also a more powerful, single motor design rather than a dual-motor belted design. Regardless! This is super exciting because it means we can start getting data that will inform the V2 drivetrain design and the hydrogen-fuel cell integration!</p>

<h3 id="some-other-important-notes">Some Other Important Notes</h3>

<p>The goals for this initial drive train were to get the bike running to a point where we could start collecting data. It was also to allow our team to start figuring out how to integrate all the components of a hydrogen bike together and figure out what the system’s layout would look like.</p>

<ul>
  <li>The current system uses a small T-Motor U15, and the bike can accelerate slowly up to around 35mph.</li>
  <li>The current drivetrain draws a maximum of 35-40A of current from the battery, while the battery is capable of 350A before the main fuse blows.</li>
</ul>

<p>The V1 drivetrain will not be part of an official release, we won’t be releasing detailed documentation on it because the performance, build quality, and safety are not near where we want them to be. We will be focusing on the design of the V2 drivetrain, which is the first one we plan on releasing should the safety be at a standard we are comfortable with.</p>

<h2 id="battery-information">Battery Information</h2>

<p>The Lithium battery in our system is used to absorb power during regenerative braking while also providing the power needed during acceleration. The Fuel Cell will recharge the battery while the bike is driving (similar to a hybrid vehicle), and also provide most of the power during steady-state driving.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gen/blog/batt_cells.jpeg" width="45%" /> <img src="/assets/images/gen/blog/batt_assembly.jpeg" width="45%" /></p>

<p>Over the past few weeks, our team has been hard at work assembling the version 1 battery. The battery is a 50V 32Ah pack built using <a href="https://batteryhookup.com/collections/spim08hp-accessories/products/2x-spim08hp-3-7v-8ah-cells-with-threaded-insert">SPIM08HP cells</a>. These cells are high-current, Lithium-Ion pouch cells with low internal resistance making them capable of providing, and sinking large currents. This, and their modular assembly structure made them perfect for the first, proof-of-concept battery.</p>

<figure>
  <a href="" target="\_blank">
    <img src="/assets/images/gen/content/team_batt.jpg" alt="battery team" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    <h4>Our battery team after completing some of the initial steps of assembly!</h4>
    <p>(Lucas, Miguel, Ebby, + Adi)</p>
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Over the next few weeks we will be integrating and testing some key safety features onto the bike including a proper emergency stop as well as some driver control switches. We’re also going to be releasing a battery build video as well as extensive documentation on the design and the construction of our battery system including issues during manufacturing and how we resolved them, tests we ran and how to safely determine the battery is operating correctly.</p>

<p>We’re also starting to transition to building up the hydrogen power system of the bike, we’re working on mounting the fuel tank and will start running benchtop tests on the fuel cell soon! <strong>Our goal is to have the bike driving under hydrogen power by the middle of the summer!</strong> Stay tuned for more updates!</p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We just hit the first major milestone of our project, having the bike drive on its own power.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/gen/blog/drive.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/gen/blog/drive.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Primary Partner—Doosan Mobility Innovation (DMI)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023-4-7-partnering-doosan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Primary Partner—Doosan Mobility Innovation (DMI)" /><published>2023-04-07T06:25:30-04:00</published><updated>2023-04-07T06:25:30-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/partnering-doosan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023-4-7-partnering-doosan/"><![CDATA[<p>We’re super excited to announce our partnership with Doosan Mobility Innovation (DMI)! DMI is a leader in small-scale fuel cell technology and has lots of experience developing fuel cells for agricultural and industrial drones.</p>

<p>Our goal is to develop a hybrid battery/hydrogen fuel-cell motorcycle as a proof of concept for hydrogen vehicles, and to develop and prove a design methodology for hydrogen vehicles to publish it open-source. For the first version of our prototype, we’ll be using <a href="https://www.doosanmobility.com/en/products/powerpack-dm15/">Doosan’s DM/DP15 Fuel Cell Power Pack</a> because of its small scale but high power output.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gen/blog/doosan_1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>We’re comitted to working in detail with Doosan engineers to realize the prototype and concept in hardware. Along the way, Doosan engineers alongside our team will address many challenges for small-scale hydrogen vehicles while also addressing critical safety standards for these vehicles.</p>

<p>Thanks so much Doosan! We’re looking forward to working with you!</p>

<h2 id="resource-links">Resource Links</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/press-releases/2023-03-29/mit-s-electric-vehicle-team-partners-with-dmi-to-create-one-of-the-first-ever-open-source-hydrogen-fuel-cell-powered">Bloomberg Press Release</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/mit-s-electric-vehicle-team-partners-with-dmi-to-create-one-of-the-first-ever-open-source-hydrogen-fuel-cell-powered-motorcycles-4f414633?mod=Searchresults">WSJ Press Release</a></p>

<p><a href="http://miters.mit.edu/large_media/MITERS_Journal_Fall_2022.pdf">MITERS Journal—MIT EVT + DMI</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Announcements" /><category term="Partnerships" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are partnering with DMI, a leader in fuel cell technology for drones and small vehicles.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">We Have a New Home!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023-3-11-new-home/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Have a New Home!" /><published>2023-03-12T07:11:11-04:00</published><updated>2023-03-12T07:11:11-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/new-home</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023-3-11-new-home/"><![CDATA[<p>We have a new home in MIT’s building N52! Welcome to room 318k in the Milkdrop Shop at the <a href="https://edgerton.mit.edu">MIT Edgerton Center</a>. This is our new home-base of operations alongside <a href="http://d-lab.mit.edu">MIT D-Lab</a> and <a href="http://miters.mit.edu">MITERS</a>.</p>

<p>Our new space provides a safe location for experimentation with fuel cells, hydrogen gas, lithium batteries, and vehicle power trains. MITERS and MIT D-Lab will still be the main locations for mechanical fabrication, welding, and other assembly of the bike and its subsystems, but a room of our own means we can work on electronics without worrying about putting others in harm’s way. Safety will always be our top priority on this team, and now we can experiment in a controlled, isolated environment so we can determine what is and isn’t safe.</p>

<p>Check out the video tour of our new space!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gen/content/tour.MOV" alt="" /></p>

<p>Our new space has many fun features!</p>
<ul>
  <li>Large wooden benches set aside for working</li>
  <li>A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamometer">motorcycle dynamometer</a> (construction in progress) that will allow us to perform full-system powertrain characterizations without leaving the lab</li>
  <li>Electrical testing equipment, power supplies, electronic loads, and more that allow us to characterize the fuel cell, batteries, and test the bike’s electrical systems</li>
  <li>Space for storage of our sensitive components, tools, and more!</li>
</ul>

<p>Wanna come say hi? We’re ususally around on Saturdays! Come check out the space and meet the team!</p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Announcements" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Check out our new space in MIT's Milkdrop shop equipped with a dynamometer, and a brand new neon sign!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/gen/content/neon.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/gen/content/neon.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">MITERS Journal — Fall 2022 Edition!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023-1-21-miters-journal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MITERS Journal — Fall 2022 Edition!" /><published>2023-01-21T06:11:11-05:00</published><updated>2023-01-21T06:11:11-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/miters-journal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023-1-21-miters-journal/"><![CDATA[<p>MITERS is a student-run shop on campus that’s responsible for many crazy creations. It is also our home. The hydrogen bike project started out of MITERS, and we continue to have a close relationship with the society. Learn more about MITERS <a href="http://miters.mit.edu">here.</a></p>

<p>Every so-often we get a new edition of the <a href="http://miters.mit.edu/miters-journal/">MITERS Journal</a> where members write up all their crazy projects to share with the world! Check out the <a href="http://miters.mit.edu/large_media/MITERS_Journal_Fall_2022.pdf">Fall 2022 Edition</a> to see some info on the hydrogen bike project!</p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Check out the overview of our project in the MITERS Fall Journal!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/gen/projects/bike1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/gen/projects/bike1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Version 1 Drive Unit — Design + Build Video</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022-12-28-gearbox-build-video/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Version 1 Drive Unit — Design + Build Video" /><published>2022-12-28T06:11:11-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-28T06:11:11-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/gearbox-build-video</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022-12-28-gearbox-build-video/"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/94Xf_wgISU4" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Our goal for the next few months is to develop a version 1 prototype of a hydrogen powered motorcycle so we can begin to characterize such a system and verify our design methodology. Over the past six months we’ve been working on the first iteration of the main drive unit.</p>

<h1 id="drive-unit-version-1">Drive Unit Version 1</h1>

<p>The drive unit is a modified gearbox from a Ducati 900SS chosen because the gearbox of the bike is structural (as in the rear swing-arm mounts to the gearbox). Designing and manufacturing a new gearbox with swing-arm mount capabilities was too much of an investement for a first prototype so we designed around the existing casing.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gen/blog/gb-3.png" alt="Gearbox belt system from the above video" /></p>

<p>The drive unit contains two T-Motor U15s putting out a maximum of around 7kW each. The motors are belted together through a 1:1 drive reduction, and then the shaft driven by both motors is belted to an output shaft that drives the main chain through a 1.4:1 belt reduction geared for torque. Each motor is controlled by its own, off the shelf, 200A-VESC motor controller. The off-the-shelf motor controllers will be used in version 1, and we will switch to a custom inverter in the future.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gen/blog/gb-4.png" alt="T-motor with dowel pins being glued" /></p>

<p>Torque transfer was done with either dowel pins from motors to hubs, and hubs to pullies, or directly through the 1/2” Aluminum Hex-Shaft construction of the gearbox. In the future we will be adding a “hat” for the gearbox that contains both motor controllers, all the wires, as well as the battery management system and any power converters needed for the rest of the bike. Note that more details on the design will be presented on the documentation pages for the Power Unit when they are released, we just need some time to verify the system and test it on real hardware before compiling the documentation.</p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Motors, belt drives, and white-lithium grease.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/gen/blog/gb-2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/gen/blog/gb-2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Project Update # 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022-12-11-project-update-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project Update # 2" /><published>2022-12-11T07:22:22-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-11T07:22:22-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/project-update-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022-12-11-project-update-2/"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/HRsTufjYouc" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>A brief engineering update from Adi on the work we’ve done on the bike so far and our plans moving forward! We’ll be releasing a white-paper soon with further details and more updates as the hardware assembly progresses!</p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Engineering update on project status (#2)]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">We got a motorcycle! And she’s a beauty!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022-12-11-toothless-the-bike%20copy%202/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We got a motorcycle! And she’s a beauty!" /><published>2022-12-11T06:11:11-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-11T06:11:11-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/toothless-the-bike%20copy%202</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022-12-11-toothless-the-bike%20copy%202/"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uzFE93WCY7U" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>A hugeeeeee thank you goes to Madhouse Motors from Boston, MA today for selling us this amazing Ducati 900ss track bike! And her name is ‘toothless’ based on her resemblence to our favorite animated dragon!</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We will modify this motorcycle by adding a high-capacity lithum battery, hydrogen fuel cell, electric motors, and associated power electronics to prove the efficacy of hydrogen powered vehicles in the real world.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We chose a motorcyle as the desired vehicle to modify (first, because we love motorcycles) but also because motorcycles are incredibally light-weight vehicles and get significantly better fuel efficiency on average than a typical car. They also have some contraints on size that are challenging when approaching the system-design of a hydrogen engine. We thought this made a motorcycle the perfect test-bed for the initial stages of our project, and one that we could scale up to larger vehicles.</p>

<p>Say hello to toothless!</p>

<h2 id="resource-links">Resource Links</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.madhousemotors.com">Mahouse Motors Boston</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Announcements" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Meet 'Toothless', a 2000 Ducati 900ss track bike, and our new ride XD]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/gen/blog/bike-2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/gen/blog/bike-2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">We are building a hydrogen powered motorcycle!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022-12-10-hydrogen-powered-bike-intro/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We are building a hydrogen powered motorcycle!" /><published>2022-12-10T04:07:30-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-10T04:07:30-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/hydrogen-powered-bike-intro</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022-12-10-hydrogen-powered-bike-intro/"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/pr1scea9tzs" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>L2F hydrogen racing started as a class project for the <a href="https://web.mit.edu/2.70/">MIT 2.70 FUNdaMENTALs of Precision Product Design</a> class and has grown into a MIT student team focusing on building a cleaner future with hydrogen. We are a re-vamping of MIT’s Electric Vehicle team which has a long history of research into renewable energy, and electric powered vehicles both in the performance and practical spheres.</p>

<p>Initially the goal was to build something cool, but through research for the project we found that sources and knowledge-bases for hydrogen-powered vehicles were limited in scope and much of the details of the technology were proprietary. We concluded that a project that focuses on an open-source hydrogen engine would be important to building a cleaner future.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Our goal with this project is to develop a platform to analyze the performance and potential of Hydrogen Fuel Cell that can serve as a robust test bed for future development towards alternatives to BEVs. What we really want to create is a open-source knowledge base. A base that others can use to develop this technology even further to implementation. The open-source community has solved many of the world’s challenges in the past by sharing knowledge and collaborating on difficult problems—we believe this is necessary right now for the realization of FCEVs.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Over the next year we hope to realize our design as a fully assembled motorcycle and verify our design methodology on the track. We have also identified key future research areas which are presented in a paper we will release soon.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We believe that hydrogen could be the future of transportation if design surrounding these vehicles is intelligent and safe. Hydrogen vehicles solve the long charge times of electic vehicles, address the power density issues of solar vehicles, and (with super capacitor technology) can also eliminate the need for heavy, and harmful lithium batteries.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Our goals are to build an open-source set of hardware for hydrogen powered vehicles, and a design methodology for these vehicles. We hope these will serve as resources for both the open source community and industry to accelerate the development of hydrogen powered vehicles bringing us towards a cleaner future.</p>

<p>(In this video, Adi takes us through what we want to do in this project and why we think it might work).</p>

<h2 id="resource-links">Resource Links</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/technology-30691393">Toyota Open Sources its Hydrogen Patents</a></p>

<p><a href="https://pressroom.toyota.com/trucking-world-endorses-toyotas-hydrogen-powered-fuel-cells-as-a-step-toward-a-cleaner-planet/">Toyota Hydrogen Fuel Cell Trucks</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.foxnews.com/auto/toyota-hydrogen-powered-pickup-suv">Toyota Unveils Hydrogen Pickup Truck + SUV</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Announcements" /><category term="Engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A little bit of history on the project, and some brief details :)]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>