<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-10-02T22:23:14-04:00</updated><id>https://licence-to-fab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">MIT Electric Vehicle Team (EVT)</title><entry><title type="html">Come See us at the Hydrogen Americas Summit!</title><link href="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-9-29-has/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Come See us at the Hydrogen Americas Summit!" /><published>2023-09-29T05:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-29T05:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/has</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-9-29-has/"><![CDATA[<p>We’re super excited to be going to the <a href="https://www.hydrogen-americas-summit.com">2023 Hydrogen Americas Summit</a> on October 2nd and 3rd at the Ronald Regan International Trade Center in Washington DC! Come checkout our motorcycle platform on the Upper Oculus (mezzanine section) right next to the registration desk!</p>

<p>Adi and Ebby from our team will also be speaking on the H2 Tech stage about the benefits of open source technology in the Hydrogen energy transition, as well as announcing some new and exciting collaborations and partnerships in relation to our work with Hydrogen in emerging markets! <strong>See them from 1:45-2:00PM on the H2 Tech Stage!</strong></p>

<p>The best part? The exhibition is <a href="https://www.hydrogen-americas-summit.com/registration/">FREE for the public</a>!</p>

<p>Additionally, follow our <a href="https://www.instagram.com/mit.evt/">Instagram</a> for live updates from the event and our road trip to the event! Get to know the team and more about our project! <i class="fab fa-instagram"></i></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gen/content/team_photo.jpg" alt="" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Announcements" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[October 2nd and 3rd at the Ronald Regan International Trade Center, Washington DC.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/blog/has.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/blog/has.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">MIT EVT’s For Good &amp;lt;3 Agreement</title><link href="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-8-21-for_good/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MIT EVT’s For Good &amp;lt;3 Agreement" /><published>2023-07-23T05:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-23T05:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/for_good</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-8-21-for_good/"><![CDATA[<p>We are pleased to announce the <u>For Good <i class="fa-solid fa-heart"></i></u> Agreement as an addition to the <a href="/terms-and-conditions/">MIT EVT Open Source Policy</a>! The <u>For Good <i class="fa-solid fa-heart"></i></u> Agreement states the following about uses of any technology we develop.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>MIT Electric Vehicle Team Open Source Policy FOR GOOD AGREEMENT
Effective Immediately as of August, 2023

By accessing content, or material produced by our team that is published on this
website, or in any journal, conference, or proceeding in any publically avaliable 
format including but not limited to written, video, visual, or any other form of 
media or information dissemination, you hereby agree to use the material for good. 
The use of the technology for good is defined as uses that positively, and 
productively benefit humanity and the environment, and any use of this technology for 
harming individuals or the environment, supporting the spread of mis-information, 
exclusion or discrimination of any group based on race, sexual orientation, beliefs, 
or any other factor will result in an immediate, irrevocable termination of your 
rights to use our work without review.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>We added the above statement to our <a href="/terms-and-conditions/">Open Source Policy</a> covering all uses of our technology and projects because we <strong>strongly believe that our technology should not be used to harm the planet or any individuals living on it.</strong> We do not expect this to be an issue for a majority of our users, but ill-intentioned and ill-informed people exist, and we hope that by adding this statement to our Open Source Policy, it will at least make people think twice about what they use our projects for.</p>

<p>That being said <strong>if you have concers about how you’re using the information we disseminate on this site in your work, please reach out. We are always willing to help individuals to make informed ethical decisions.</strong></p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Announcements" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[MIT EVT releases a new addition to the open source policy that bounds uses of its technology for the good of the planet.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Version 1 Battery Documentation Released</title><link href="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-7-23-battery_docs_v1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Version 1 Battery Documentation Released" /><published>2023-07-23T05:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-23T05:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/battery_docs_v1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-7-23-battery_docs_v1/"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hdNO4Q_LAoQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>After a few months of work we’re really excited to announce our version 1 battery system and its associated documentation! It’s worth noting that this first version battery system is a <em>prototype system</em> that’s mainly intended for us to collect data during the initial stages of research. It will be followed by a more complete, optimized, and detailed battery design within the next 6 months that’s based on data collected from version 1, performance requirements of the vehicle, as well as simulation.</p>

<h3 id="version-1-essbattery-specifications">Version 1 ESS/Battery Specifications</h3>
<ul>
  <li>System Voltage: 50V (12s)</li>
  <li>System Capacity: 32Ah</li>
  <li>Cells: SPIM08HP (16Ah)</li>
  <li>Configuration: 12s2p</li>
</ul>

<p>The associated documentation is split into two main components, detailed information on specifically the version 1 battery system itself, and tools developed for general battery systems development. Documentation specific to the version 1 ESS includes documentation on cell choices, mechanical design and structure, BMS system setup, and Mechanical CAD of the battery. This documentation is intended for <em>hobbyists to replicate this battery for use in light-duty electric vehicle systems.</em></p>

<p>Tools developed for general battery systems development include a document outlining cell internal resistance measurement, and methods for pack and module-level resistance matching to optimize battery performance. We have also released a <strong>Python script that can take cell resistance data as an input, and output a resistance-matched pack configuration.</strong> The output is not optimal, but we will develop the tool further for release in the next version. It is likely good enough for most applications on <strong>Solar Car and FSAE teams, or hobby-grade vehicles.</strong> But, it should likely not be used for commercial application at the moment.</p>

<p><strong>Please note that contributions to our documentation, and suggested edits for clarity or function are always welcome.</strong></p>

<h2 id="documentation-links">Documentation Links</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/Licence-to-Fab/battery-design/blob/main/Documentation/Version%201%20ESS%20Docs.pdf">Version 1 Energy Management System Design + Docs</a><i class="fa-brands fa-creative-commons"></i></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/Licence-to-Fab/battery-design/tree/main/Mechanical-CAD/V1">Mechanical CAD for Version 1 ESS (STEP)</a><i class="fa-brands fa-creative-commons"></i></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/Licence-to-Fab/battery-design/tree/main/Tools">Individual Cell Resistance Data + Impedance Matching Script</a><i class="fa-brands fa-creative-commons"></i></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/Licence-to-Fab/battery-design/blob/main/Documentation/Battery_Modeling___Internal_Resistance_Matching.pdf">Procedures for Battery Internal Resistance Measurement + Matching</a><i class="fa-brands fa-creative-commons"></i></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/Licence-to-Fab/battery-design/tree/main">MIT EVT Battery Design Github Repository</a><i class="fa-brands fa-creative-commons"></i></p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Announcements" /><category term="Engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[MIT EVT releases design details on Version 1 Energy Storage System (ESS) as well as additional tools for battery design.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/blog/battery2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/blog/battery2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Primary Partner—Ducati Motor Holding</title><link href="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-7-13-ducati/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Primary Partner—Ducati Motor Holding" /><published>2023-07-13T05:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-13T05:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/ducati</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-7-13-ducati/"><![CDATA[<p>We’re super excited to be partnering with Ducati Motor Holding! Ducati combines skill, design, passion, and a long racing pedigree to make some of the best motorcycles in the world. They’re a standard for both design and engineering, and they’re a company that we look up to in our own work.</p>

<p>Our journey with Ducati started from the very early stages of our project. The bike we acquired to convert to hydrogen power is a Ducati 900ss from the 1999-2000 era. A few months later we acquired another Ducati, a 750ss from the same era, to use as an evaluation bike. We love working on these bikes, they’re spacious, easy to work on, well-engineered, and beautiful to look at. Now we’re super excited to be working with Ducati further as we evaluate hydrogen power for use in race bikes, and touring bikes.</p>

<p>Together, we hope to build robust solutions to the climate crisis while maintaining the characteristics we love about motorcycles, and racing. We think this partnership is key to truly making an impact in the world of motorcycling, and we’re super excited to see what it means for the future of transportation, and the planet.</p>

<h2 id="resource-links">Resource Links</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.ducati.com/us/en/home">Ducati Official Website (US)</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.ducati.com/ww/en/company/innovation/moto-e">Ducati MotoE</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Announcements" /><category term="Partnerships" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[MIT and Ducati partner to explore the future of hydrogen power in motorcycles.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/blog/ducati.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/blog/ducati.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Wild Rabbit Moto Show!</title><link href="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-5-20-wildrabbit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wild Rabbit Moto Show!" /><published>2023-05-20T06:25:30-04:00</published><updated>2023-05-20T06:25:30-04:00</updated><id>https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/wildrabbit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-5-20-wildrabbit/"><![CDATA[<p>Today, a HUGE thank-you goes out to our family at <a href="https://www.madhousemotors.com">Madhouse Motors</a> accross the river in Boston, and <a href="https://www.nacocentral.com">Naco Taco</a> in our own backyard for hosting the <a href="https://www.instagram.com/wildrabbitmotoshow/?hl=en">Wild Rabbit Community Moto Show 2023!</a> Thanks to J. Shia and Madhouse for building such an amazing community we are proud to be a part of, and for hosing a super fun event!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gen/blog/wild_rabbit_2.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Thanks to everyone who stopped by our booth and voted for our hydrogen-powered motorcycle which took home the “Best in Show” and “Best Creative Mod” awards this year! Thanks again to <a href="https://www.instagram.com/jshia/">J. Shia</a> and the Madhouse team for this award. It means so much to us coming from such amazing artists and engineers like yourselves! Check out their work guys! It’s awesome!</p>

<p>It was super fun to meet everyone and see your awesome builds! We hope to collaborate with you all in the future and we hope to see everyone again next year!</p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Racing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[MIT EVT takes the "Best in Show" and "Best Creative Mod" awards at the Wild Rabbit Community Moto Show 2023!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/blog/wild_rabbit_1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/blog/wild_rabbit_1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Roaming on Battery Power!</title><link href="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-4-27-roaming/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Roaming on Battery Power!" /><published>2023-04-27T06:25:30-04:00</published><updated>2023-04-27T06:25:30-04:00</updated><id>https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/roaming</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-4-27-roaming/"><![CDATA[<p>Today we’re super excited to announce that our team just hit the first major milestone on the road to developing a hydrogen powered motorcycle! Our bike drives under its own power. In this case, the bike was powered by a Lithium battery. Here’s a few fun videos of it driving!</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/oQHbWxG8HFY" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/XX5TXS8L-wE" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="https://youtube.com/shorts/5WhaHTfYNqE?feature=share">Here’s another short driving clip,</a></p>

<h2 id="drivetrain-notes">Drivetrain Notes</h2>

<p>This was not completely without issues, we noticed while driving the bike that one of the belts connecting the second motor to the main drive shaft was slipping. This is a simple issue to fix but one that prevented us from trying to drive the bike any faster. Over the next few weeks, we’ll be doing the following.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Dropping out the V1 drivetrain and attempting to correct the belt slipping issue.</li>
  <li>Focusing on the design of the V2 drivetrain to get that mounted on the bike by mid-summer.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gen/blog/testing1.jpeg" width="45%" /> <img src="/assets/images/gen/blog/testing2.jpeg" width="45%" /></p>

<p>The V2 drivetrain will have a better mechanical design and also a more powerful, single motor design rather than a dual-motor belted design. Regardless! This is super exciting because it means we can start getting data that will inform the V2 drivetrain design and the hydrogen-fuel cell integration!</p>

<h3 id="some-other-important-notes">Some Other Important Notes</h3>

<p>The goals for this initial drive train were to get the bike running to a point where we could start collecting data. It was also to allow our team to start figuring out how to integrate all the components of a hydrogen bike together and figure out what the system’s layout would look like.</p>

<ul>
  <li>The current system uses a small T-Motor U15, and the bike can accelerate slowly up to around 35mph.</li>
  <li>The current drivetrain draws a maximum of 35-40A of current from the battery, while the battery is capable of 350A before the main fuse blows.</li>
</ul>

<p>The V1 drivetrain will not be part of an official release, we won’t be releasing detailed documentation on it because the performance, build quality, and safety are not near where we want them to be. We will be focusing on the design of the V2 drivetrain, which is the first one we plan on releasing should the safety be at a standard we are comfortable with.</p>

<h2 id="battery-information">Battery Information</h2>

<p>The Lithium battery in our system is used to absorb power during regenerative braking while also providing the power needed during acceleration. The Fuel Cell will recharge the battery while the bike is driving (similar to a hybrid vehicle), and also provide most of the power during steady-state driving.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gen/blog/batt_cells.jpeg" width="45%" /> <img src="/assets/images/gen/blog/batt_assembly.jpeg" width="45%" /></p>

<p>Over the past few weeks, our team has been hard at work assembling the version 1 battery. The battery is a 50V 32Ah pack built using <a href="https://batteryhookup.com/collections/spim08hp-accessories/products/2x-spim08hp-3-7v-8ah-cells-with-threaded-insert">SPIM08HP cells</a>. These cells are high-current, Lithium-Ion pouch cells with low internal resistance making them capable of providing, and sinking large currents. This, and their modular assembly structure made them perfect for the first, proof-of-concept battery.</p>

<figure>
  <a href="" target="\_blank">
    <img src="/assets/images/gen/content/team_batt.jpg" alt="battery team" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    <h4>Our battery team after completing some of the initial steps of assembly!</h4>
    <p>(Lucas, Miguel, Ebby, + Adi)</p>
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Over the next few weeks we will be integrating and testing some key safety features onto the bike including a proper emergency stop as well as some driver control switches. We’re also going to be releasing a battery build video as well as extensive documentation on the design and the construction of our battery system including issues during manufacturing and how we resolved them, tests we ran and how to safely determine the battery is operating correctly.</p>

<p>We’re also starting to transition to building up the hydrogen power system of the bike, we’re working on mounting the fuel tank and will start running benchtop tests on the fuel cell soon! <strong>Our goal is to have the bike driving under hydrogen power by the middle of the summer!</strong> Stay tuned for more updates!</p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We just hit the first major milestone of our project, having the bike drive on its own power.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/blog/drive.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/blog/drive.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Primary Partner—Doosan Mobility Innovation (DMI)</title><link href="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-4-7-partnering-doosan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Primary Partner—Doosan Mobility Innovation (DMI)" /><published>2023-04-07T06:25:30-04:00</published><updated>2023-04-07T06:25:30-04:00</updated><id>https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/partnering-doosan</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-4-7-partnering-doosan/"><![CDATA[<p>We’re super excited to announce our partnership with Doosan Mobility Innovation (DMI)! DMI is a leader in small-scale fuel cell technology and has lots of experience developing fuel cells for agricultural and industrial drones.</p>

<p>Our goal is to develop a hybrid battery/hydrogen fuel-cell motorcycle as a proof of concept for hydrogen vehicles, and to develop and prove a design methodology for hydrogen vehicles to publish it open-source. For the first version of our prototype, we’ll be using <a href="https://www.doosanmobility.com/en/products/powerpack-dm15/">Doosan’s DM/DP15 Fuel Cell Power Pack</a> because of its small scale but high power output.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gen/blog/doosan_1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>We’re comitted to working in detail with Doosan engineers to realize the prototype and concept in hardware. Along the way, Doosan engineers alongside our team will address many challenges for small-scale hydrogen vehicles while also addressing critical safety standards for these vehicles.</p>

<p>Thanks so much Doosan! We’re looking forward to working with you!</p>

<h2 id="resource-links">Resource Links</h2>

<p><a href="http://miters.mit.edu/large_media/MITERS_Journal_Fall_2022.pdf">MITERS Journal—MIT EVT + DMI</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Announcements" /><category term="Partnerships" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are partnering with DMI, a leader in fuel cell technology for drones and small vehicles.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">We Have a New Home!</title><link href="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-3-11-new-home/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Have a New Home!" /><published>2023-03-12T07:11:11-04:00</published><updated>2023-03-12T07:11:11-04:00</updated><id>https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/new-home</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-3-11-new-home/"><![CDATA[<p>We have a new home in MIT’s building N52! Welcome to room 318k in the Milkdrop Shop at the <a href="https://edgerton.mit.edu">MIT Edgerton Center</a>. This is our new home-base of operations alongside <a href="http://d-lab.mit.edu">MIT D-Lab</a> and <a href="http://miters.mit.edu">MITERS</a>.</p>

<p>Our new space provides a safe location for experimentation with fuel cells, hydrogen gas, lithium batteries, and vehicle power trains. MITERS and MIT D-Lab will still be the main locations for mechanical fabrication, welding, and other assembly of the bike and its subsystems, but a room of our own means we can work on electronics without worrying about putting others in harm’s way. Safety will always be our top priority on this team, and now we can experiment in a controlled, isolated environment so we can determine what is and isn’t safe.</p>

<p>Check out the video tour of our new space!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gen/content/tour.MOV" alt="" /></p>

<p>Our new space has many fun features!</p>
<ul>
  <li>Large wooden benches set aside for working</li>
  <li>A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamometer">motorcycle dynamometer</a> (construction in progress) that will allow us to perform full-system powertrain characterizations without leaving the lab</li>
  <li>Electrical testing equipment, power supplies, electronic loads, and more that allow us to characterize the fuel cell, batteries, and test the bike’s electrical systems</li>
  <li>Space for storage of our sensitive components, tools, and more!</li>
</ul>

<p>Wanna come say hi? We’re ususally around on Saturdays! Come check out the space and meet the team!</p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Announcements" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Check out our new space in MIT's Milkdrop shop equipped with a dynamometer, and a brand new neon sign!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/content/neon.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/content/neon.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">MITERS Journal — Fall 2022 Edition!</title><link href="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-1-21-miters-journal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MITERS Journal — Fall 2022 Edition!" /><published>2023-01-21T06:11:11-05:00</published><updated>2023-01-21T06:11:11-05:00</updated><id>https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/miters-journal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2023-1-21-miters-journal/"><![CDATA[<p>MITERS is a student-run shop on campus that’s responsible for many crazy creations. It is also our home. The hydrogen bike project started out of MITERS, and we continue to have a close relationship with the society. Learn more about MITERS <a href="http://miters.mit.edu">here.</a></p>

<p>Every so-often we get a new edition of the <a href="http://miters.mit.edu/miters-journal/">MITERS Journal</a> where members write up all their crazy projects to share with the world! Check out the <a href="http://miters.mit.edu/large_media/MITERS_Journal_Fall_2022.pdf">Fall 2022 Edition</a> to see some info on the hydrogen bike project!</p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Check out the overview of our project in the MITERS Fall Journal!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/projects/bike1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/projects/bike1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Version 1 Drive Unit — Design + Build Video</title><link href="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2022-12-28-gearbox-build-video/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Version 1 Drive Unit — Design + Build Video" /><published>2022-12-28T06:11:11-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-28T06:11:11-05:00</updated><id>https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/gearbox-build-video</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/blog/2022-12-28-gearbox-build-video/"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/94Xf_wgISU4" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Our goal for the next few months is to develop a version 1 prototype of a hydrogen powered motorcycle so we can begin to characterize such a system and verify our design methodology. Over the past six months we’ve been working on the first iteration of the main drive unit.</p>

<h1 id="drive-unit-version-1">Drive Unit Version 1</h1>

<p>The drive unit is a modified gearbox from a Ducati 900SS chosen because the gearbox of the bike is structural (as in the rear swing-arm mounts to the gearbox). Designing and manufacturing a new gearbox with swing-arm mount capabilities was too much of an investement for a first prototype so we designed around the existing casing.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gen/blog/gb-3.png" alt="Gearbox belt system from the above video" /></p>

<p>The drive unit contains two T-Motor U15s putting out a maximum of around 7kW each. The motors are belted together through a 1:1 drive reduction, and then the shaft driven by both motors is belted to an output shaft that drives the main chain through a 1.4:1 belt reduction geared for torque. Each motor is controlled by its own, off the shelf, 200A-VESC motor controller. The off-the-shelf motor controllers will be used in version 1, and we will switch to a custom inverter in the future.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gen/blog/gb-4.png" alt="T-motor with dowel pins being glued" /></p>

<p>Torque transfer was done with either dowel pins from motors to hubs, and hubs to pullies, or directly through the 1/2” Aluminum Hex-Shaft construction of the gearbox. In the future we will be adding a “hat” for the gearbox that contains both motor controllers, all the wires, as well as the battery management system and any power converters needed for the rest of the bike. Note that more details on the design will be presented on the documentation pages for the Power Unit when they are released, we just need some time to verify the system and test it on real hardware before compiling the documentation.</p>]]></content><author><name>Adi Mehrotra</name></author><category term="Engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Motors, belt drives, and white-lithium grease.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/blog/gb-2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://licence-to-fab.github.io/assets/images/gen/blog/gb-2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>